# 麻
Numbing,
# 辣
spicy,
# 嫩
tender,
# 酥
crunchy,
# 鲜 香 烫
fully of umami and warm,
# 川菜的老菜 麻婆豆腐
An old traditional Sichuan dish, MapoTofu
# 先把花椒焙一下
First let's toast the Sichuan peppercorn
# 焙花椒呢 要小火
Keep on low heat when toasting, do it slowly
# 火不要大 慢慢焙
# 焙香 焙安逸些
Toast it until fragrant, until "An yi (tasty)"
# 花椒好了 晾一晾
That's ready, set it aside to cool a bit
# 这个豆腐呢 把上边这层给它片下去
Slice the top layer from the Tofu
# 今天这个豆腐 就买的是嫩豆腐
We bought the tender tofu today
# 这烧的麻婆豆腐才好吃呢 对
That's what makes the MapoTofu tasty (bingo)
# 兑点开水 稍微加点盐
Some boiling water and a pinch of salt
# 直接就给它下锅了
...and throw in the Tofu
# 这个放盐呢 就是要让豆腐通过加热
The salt helps reducing the gaminess
# 去掉豆腐的豆腥味 让豆腐的蛋白质凝固
and coagulating the protein in the tofu
# 它就出来以后不容易碎 不要动了
So that the tofu won't break easily. Now leave it, don't stir
# 像老豆腐 换一遍到两遍水
For aged tofu, you need to blanch it in fresh water twice
# 因为它那里边有卤水的味道
because there's some briny flavour left in the tofu
# 下面呢 备点料
Next some condiments,
# 郫县豆瓣酱 这是灵魂
PiXian broad bean paste, that's the absolute soul of this dish
# 这个豆瓣酱 把它剁碎以后呢
It releases all its flavours after it's finely chopped
# 味道就全部都出来了
# 这豆豉 干豆豉 洗一洗
This is dried, fermented black bean. Wash it
# 洗完了我们拿水泡上
... and soak it in water.
# 我这也是 搁一块
Just combine with the bean paste
# 这豆豉一定要剁 不剁那香味释放不出来
You have to chop the bean also, or else the fragrance is trapped inside
# 为什么要放一块剁呢
But why chopping them together?
# 它这个豆豉不容易跑
Because the bean won't run off easily
# 它有豆瓣酱揽着它
as it's been trapped by the gooey paster.
# 好了 花椒凉了啊
Alrighty, the Sichuan peppercorn is cooled
# 做椒盐儿啊 花椒面啊
You have to toast the peppercorn fresh, when making pepper-salt and ground pepper
# 都是要现焙 香
# 花椒还是用多少焙多少 不要太多
You only toast as much as you need
# 搁时间长了它就没味了 麻味也少了 是
The fragrance will run off if left outside
# 你看 大爷这个你看小箩一筛
You see, it's much better after sieving
# 这就够了 传统工艺
That's it, traditional trick!
# 豆腐一开锅就闷就行
Just keep the pot warm after water boils
# 切点小料
Let's do some condiments
# 你像二伯做宫保鸡丁
Like the Kung-pao chicken ErBai made,
# 那切的是大葱花 这叫小葱花
he diced the leek larger, we dice it finer this time
# 川菜之所以好吃 这个料啊 料重 香
The real reason Sichuan dishes are so good, is they use a lot of aromatics
# 包括油啊 你看真正做 我们都用什么油啊
including even the choice of oil:
# 用菜籽油 菜籽油它比较粘稠
we use the oil made from toasted canola, which is more viscous
# 着原材料 着的比较重
it coats the ingredients better
# 出来这个菜就特别香
and that's the key to flavour!
# 青蒜 这些原材料都准备好了
Garlic sprouts, done.
# 可以开火了
It's ready to roll!
# 多倒点 花生油 剁好的牛肉末
In with oil, and minced beef
# 煸香煸透  把豆瓣酱给我 来啦
Fry it until cooked through, and pass me the bean paste!
# 豆瓣酱一定要煸香 煸酥 煸香煸酥
You have to cook the bean paste thoroughly, cook it until crunchy and fragrant
# 下葱姜小料
In with scallion and ginger
# 早一点放葱姜呢
The reason we add them early on:
# 让它一个是降低油的温度
Firstly, it cools down the oil a bit
# 二呢 让它煸出的更香一些
Secondly, it's more fragrant this way
# 这点很关键啊
That's a key point
# 你看有的快出锅了才搁辣椒面
Some add the ground chili when finishing
# 那就不对了 一定把这香气给放出来
that's very incorrect. Add it now will let it release its flavour better
# 肉一定要煸酥
Again, meet has to be cooked until crunchy
# 所谓酥呢 就是煸透
basically cook it through.
# 黄酒 再来点儿酱油
Cooking wine (Shaoxing wine), soy sauce
# 老抽 来点水 烧豆腐
Dark soy sauce, water, to stew the tofu
# 放半盆 好嘞 够了吧 好了
Half a bowl of water. - Sure! that's enough? - Just right
# 豆瓣酱啊不少 咱就不加盐了
Cuz the bean paste is already quite salty, we don't need more salt
# 略微的加点糖 你闻这味出来了
A bit of sugar though. (you can really smell it now)
# 再早啊 做麻婆豆腐不搁糖
In earlier times, you don't add sugar making MapoTofu
# 做辣菜不要搁胡椒粉
Don't add ground white pepper when making spicy dishes
# 两个辣合到一起 品尝不出来
you won't be able to taste the difference,
# 它那个味就很香了
as it's already spicy and smelling nice
# 这是老抽 这味都调好了
This is dark soy sauce, that's it with seasoning
# 我们把豆腐（放进去）
Now, tofu in
# 这个时候呢 我们为了让这个味道更加柔
To make the dish taste more balanced and coherent from bottom up,
# 从上到底 都能吃出这个味道是统一的味道
# 这时候把焙好的花椒面
We put in part of the ground Sichuan pepper now
# 可以提前烧 提前搁里边一部分
Give it some head start
# 因为我们先吃 先麻啊
# 最后出锅的时候还要撒
we add the other half when finishing
# 吃到底下底下没味啊
But that way the numbing flavour won't reach the bottom if we don't add some now
# 所以这时候先搁一点 花椒面
# 使这麻婆豆腐更入味
it blends the flavour much better
# 先咕嘟一会儿
Leave it braise for a while
# 有的为什么 有好多人烧菜不入味
Many people don't braise it long enough until slurring the dish
# 咕嘟咕嘟一开锅就勾芡了 这时间短
that's why their dishes are bland
# 都好了啊 现在咱勾芡
Now it's ready to add slurry
# 我们上次说的 勾芡不是一次勾芡
Like we said last time, in multiply rounds
# 逐步的勾芡 要分成一步两步甚至三步
...gradually, up to three times
# 中火
Put your fire to medium,
# 二次勾芡 看着啊 收汁儿
See, the second time, also reducing the sauce
# 推 推
push it away from you
# 这个豆腐呢 还有两种呈现的方式
There basically are two ways this dish is presented:
# 一种是汁儿大的
one is wee bit saucy,
# 我今天做的就是汁儿大一点儿 宽汁儿的
let's do that today, saucy kind
# 还有一种是窄汁的 有的是用砂锅上的
another kind is a bit less sauce, presented in a clay pot, or on a dish
# 有用的盘上的
# 这个配碗米饭 米饭都蒸好了
It's best with a bowl of rice,... which just happens to be ready
# 麻婆豆腐好了 关火 青蒜
Okay it's done. Fire to off, some diced garlic sprouts
# 这也是一样 也是两步 两个步骤
Same with this, two steps
# 这就行了 出锅
That's ready now, out goes the MapoTofu
# 我来 帮我装盘啊 我来出盘
Aw, let me handle that, I'll do the plating
# 抬起抬起
Raise the pan a bit
# 真地道啊
Wow, look at that good ol' traditional taste
# 最后那青蒜 画龙点睛
the bit of garlic sprouts, perfect!
# 然后花椒面
Don't forget the ground Sichuan pepper
# 因为底下有味了 上面撒均匀
Remember we put some in earlier? Just evenly spread it on top.
# 二伯 这都是VIP待遇
That's VIP service for Erbar there
# 二伯带点饭啊
Have it with some rice!
# 好吃 又嫩 真是那七个味都出来了
Damn good that is. Mixing all seven flavours:
# 麻 辣 烫 鲜 香 酥 嫩
Numbing, spicy, sizzling, umami, fragrant, crunchy and tender.
# 中国菜的灵魂在哪儿 就是融合
That's the spirits of Chinese cooking, coherence and well-balanced
# 它七个特点融合的非常到位
The flavours were blended so nicely.
# 真的大爷 这不是表扬你
Not to praise you my man, it's really, really good
# 这做的真的好
# 有网友请大爷二伯
Some of you asked DaYe and ErBai
# 讲讲不同类型的醋
what are the different kinds of vinegar in Chinese cooking
# 地方醋
Regional vinegar,
# 像山西的地方醋
like Baoning vinegar from Shanxi province,
# 重庆的
variants from Chongqing,
# 四川的地方醋
and from Sichuan,
# 它是根据某一个菜
are used on dish-to-dish basis.
# 像保宁醋做鱼香肉丝
Like you would use the Baoning vinegar to YuXiang pork,
# 宫保鸡丁用它那个醋
and for Kung-pao chicken
# 它那个醋一个是颜色也好看
Baoning vinegar is both pretty in color and stable in its acidity
# 再加上味道稳定
# 经过加热以后
It won't evaporate as fast when heated
# 它挥发的不会那么快
# 香味也很不错
Also, full in flavour.
# 镇江香醋也好
Zhengjiang vinegar is also good
# 是不是恒顺香醋也好
also is Hengshun vinegar,
# 山西老陈醋也好
and the aged ones from Shanxi province.
# 稍微适合颜色重一点这个菜
They are suitable for dishes with heavy coloring,
# 你比如说北京菜
like Beijing dishes using Beijing's rice wine vinegar
# 北京的米醋
# 你要做乌鱼蛋汤
You got to use Beijing's rice wine vinegar when making the Wuyu fish soup with egg.
# 必须得是使米醋
# 虽说香醋什么的
Although those other vinegars have more fragrance, and taste
# 味道很好
# 但是它味道太重
they are also a bit too overwhelming.
# 它就不能使这些东西
So they cannot be used in dishes like sweet-sour fish
# 包括做糖醋鱼
# 可以用米醋
You can use rice wine vinegar, or white vinegar
# 也可以用白醋
# 但是绝不能用颜色深的醋
But don't use dark-colored kinds.
# 你比如说像杭州菜的
For example in Hangzhou dishes (a city near Shanghai)
# 西湖醋鱼
West-lake vinaigrette fish,
# 它就可以用香醋
you can use vinegars like Zhengjiang vinegar
# 镇江香醋
# 现在西湖醋鱼也改了
But in recent years chefs have changed,
# 人家不在用
They no longer use Zhengjiang vinegar
# 镇江香醋
# 人家还为了柔和颜色
They mix Zhengjiang vinegar and rice wine vinegar
# 香气够拟出一种特殊的香味
to create a specific taste and color.
# 他还跟镇江香醋和米醋
# 两种醋
to create a specific taste and color.
# 调和得出来
# 西湖醋鱼
Making the West-lake vinaigrette fish taste even better.
# 所以这味道就更好
# 所以说这个东西
It all boils down to the fact that Chinese culture is quite regional,
# 就是说
# 就说我们中国文化
It all boils down to the fact that Chinese culture is quite regional,
# 还是区域地域文化
# 是吧
Right
# 每个地域的东西
The eating habit depends quite heavily on the region
# 喜欢吃它喜欢的东西
# 但是总的来说
But to summarize, if the dish is dark in color
# 颜色重的
# 是吧
But to summarize, if the dish is dark in color
# 要是可以使颜色深一点的醋
you use a darker-colored vinegar.
# 有的是增香的
Some enhances its fragrance, while some adds umami
# 有的是提鲜的
# 你看香醋
The fragrant kind is there for the specific taste.
# 他就是香
# 米醋香度就不够
Rice wine vinegar is just lacking that, because it just adds acidity
# 他只是提的酸味
# 要颜色鲜艳点好看一点
If you want pretty colors, like pan frying bean sprouts
# 另外比如炒豆芽菜
# 烹什么醋
What do you use?
# 就只能烹米醋
Rice wine vinegar, that's all you can use.
# 其它醋
If you use other kinds,
# 烹上以后
# 一个是颜色上去了
you either have too dark color,
# 二一个是味儿太重
or it's too punchy.